Bill Thomson Papers 2010.0049
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Bill Thomson Papers
undated, 1979-2010.
2010.0049
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
19.5 Linear feet
The Bill Thomson Papers contain artwork spanning from his high school days in Southington, CT to his recent picture books, Building with Dad, Chalk, Baseball Hour, Karate Hour and Soccer Hour. The collection contains sketches, models, finished artwork and illustrations from his work as the illustrator working with his wife Diann, who is the graphic designer for their firm Thomson Illustration and Design.
Thomson, Bill, 1963-
Biography
Born in Waterbury, CT, in 1963, Bill Thomson has created artwork for advertising, book, and editorial clients across the United States. Thomson’s recent work has focused primarily on children’s books, illustrating Karate Hour, Building With Dad, Baseball Hour, Chalk and Soccer Hour for Cavendish Children's Books. Thomson's artwork has received numerous awards and recognition in the country’s most prestigious juried illustration competitions, including those sponsored by the Society of Illustrators (NY), the Los Angeles Society of Illustrators, Communication Arts, Step Inside Design and Three By Three. Thomson has also received Gold and Silver Awards from the Los Angeles Society of Illustrators and the Connecticut Art Director’s Club, and his work has been exhibited in numerous group shows in New York and across the country. Thomson was the winner of 2009 Connecticut Book Award for Children’s Illustrator and was also a finalist for the award in 2005 and 2007. His books have received accolades from the National Parenting Publications (Gold Award), the International Reading Association (Children’s Book Award Notable), the American Library Association (Children’s Book Notable and Booklist Editor’s Choice), and been nominated for state book awards in Indiana, Ohio, Utah, Washington, South Dakota, Kentucky, South Carolina, Delaware, Texas, Tennessee, Kentucky and Iowa. Bill Thomson is an Associate Professor of Illustration at the Hartford Art School at the University of Hartford where he received the Award for Outstanding Teaching in 2004. Thomson lives and works in Southington, Connecticut, with his wife, Diann, and their three sons, Billy, Nik, and Ethan. To see more of Thomson’s artwork, please see http://www.billthomson.com or his blog at http://billthomsonillustration.blogspot.com/.
General note
Published Works:
Karate Hour, Marshall Cavendish, 2004.
Building with Dad, Marshall Cavendish, 2006.
Baseball hour, Marshall Cavendish, 2008.
Chalk, Marshall Cavendish, 2010.
Soccer Hour, Marshall Cavendish, 2011.
Scope and Content
The Bill Thomson Papers consist of sketches, finished artwork, models, advertising artwork, and artwork created during Thomson's student days as well as documenting his life as a professional illustrator. There are also five panels documenting the creative process in the life of a brochure.
Arrangement
The Papers are arranged in two series, with Series I containing the bulk of the collection in seven boxes generally arranged by book project. Series II consists of the works of art in Art Storage.
Series I: Preliminary and Finished Artwork, Photographs, Research Materials ( 1979-2010 )
Series II: Exhibit panels and paintings ( undated )
Acquisition Information
Bill Thomson began transferring his papers to the Northeast Children's Literature Collection in 2010.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to [children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Hartford Art School.; Syracuse University.; Thomson, Bill, 1963-; Thomson, William.; University of Hartford.; Authors.; Books.; Children's literature--Connecticut authors.; Children's literature--Connecticut illustrators.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works).; Fliers. [printed matter]; Galley proofs.; Illustrated children's books.; Illustrations (visual works).; Illustrators.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographs.; Posters.; Professors.; Publications.; Sketches.; Southington (Conn.); Waterbury (Conn.); Works of art.
- Series I: Preliminary and Finished Artwork, Photographs, Research Materials, 1979-2010
  - Building with Dad (New York: Marshall Cavendish, 2006) (Box 1)
    - Finished Artwork
    - Text
    - Pencil sketches (9 pieces)
    - Photographs (509)
    - Magazines with pictures of construction equipment
    - Production proofs (Black and white)
  - Chalk (New York: Marshall Cavendish, 2010) (Box 2)
    - Sketches (24 pieces)
    - Photographs (435)
    - Three models of dinosaurs
    - Production proofs (Black and white)
  - Baseball Hour (New York: Marshall Cavendish, 2008) (Box 3)
    - Finished Artwork
    - Correspondence
    - Pencil sketches (9 pieces)
    - Complete color proof
    - Photographs (330)
    - Production proofs (Black and white)
  - Karate Hour (New York: Marshall Cavendish, 2004) (Box 4)
    - Text
    - Finished Artwork
    - Color proofs
    - Pencil sketches (15 pieces)
    - Photographs (421)
    - Black and white reproduction
  - Paintings and Drawings for Building with Dad, Chalk, Baseball Hour and Karate Hour (16) (Box 5)
  - College and high school artwork (Box 6)
  - Photographs
  - Ink wash (1st use of technique)
  - College and high school artwork (Box 7)
  - Serials and Cover illustrations
  - Interior illustrations
  - College artwork (oversize), 1980-1984 (Oversize Folder)
    Scope and Content Note
    Artwork (12) done during college (1980-1984). Media include pencil, pen and ink, watercolor, collage.
- Series II: Exhibit panels and paintings, undated
  - Exhibit panels for "The Miracles of Teamwork" (5) (Other Art Storage, Oversize Art Storage)
  - Painting of a baseball (1) (Oversize Art Storage)
  - Painting of a girl with man (1) (Oversize Art Storage)